Guide to the Howard Rheingold Papers M1882
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Howard Rheingold papers
circa 1975-2003
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Rheingold, Howard.
M1882
2.75 Linear Feet: 2 cartons, 1 box, 1 half-box
The papers of writer and technologist Howard Rheingold include drafts, proposals, and other typescripts; notes; fliers; and many articles and videos by and about him.
Biographical / Historical
Howard Rheingold (b.1947) is an author, teacher, and critic whose focus is primarily on technology and communication media. He is credited with creating the term "virtual communities." Rheingold was active on the WELL computer network beginning in 1985. He was editor of Whole Earth Review and the Millennium Whole Earth Catalog (1994). He was the first Executive Editor of HotWired and founded Electric Minds in 1996. In addition to the books Tools for Thought (1984), Virtual Reality (1991), The Virtual Community (1993), Smart Mobs (2002) and Net Smart (2012), Rheingold has written the "Tomorrow" newspaper column as well as articles in several other newspapers and magazines. He has worked with the Institute for the Future and was the first research fellow there in 2008. He has also been a lecturer at University of California, Berkeley and Stanford University, and he leads the online learning community Rheingold U.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use. Audiovisual and born-digital materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Acquisition Information
This collection given by Howard Rheingold to Stanford University, Special Collections, 2012-2015.
Rheingold, Howard.; Rheingold, Howard.
- Series I: Media
  - VHS tape (commercial): Thinking Allowed with Dr. Jeffrey Mishlove: Howard Rheingold Tools for Thought, 1988 (Box 1, Videotape 1)
  - VHS tape: Howard Rheingold Rough Cut Promo 1/24/2003 (Box 1, Videotape 2)
  - VHS tape: PBS Video MacNeil Lehrer Newshour 10/19/1994 Howard Rheingold (Box 1, Videotape 3)
  - VHS tape: Today - Virtual Reality 12/2/1991 (Box 1, Videotape 4)
  - VHS tape: Howard Rheingold Primetime Live 12/9/1993, mold on tape pack (Box 1, Videotape 5)
  - VHS tape: Howard Rheingold NBC Nightly News 3/19/2003 (Box 1, Videotape 6)
  - VHS tape: Electric Minds Promo Marketing Video and VNR 10/25/1996 (Box 1, Videotape 7)
  - VHS tape: Pop! Tech 2002 Session 2 New Human Societies in Cyberspace Howard Rheingold, Amy Bruckman, Moderator: Steve Larsen (Box 1, Videotape 8)
  - VHS tape: Kinko's "Howard Rheingold Intro 1" :30 (Box 1, Videotape 9)
  - VHS tape: CBS News "Electronic Town Meet" (Box 1, Videotape 10)
  - VHS tape: Rheingold, Howard Milennium Whole Earth Catalog "Good Morning America" Nov. 1994, 5 mins. Original (Box 1, Videotape 11)
  - VHS tape: Howard Rheingold/ABC News 12/23/2002 Smart Mobs (Box 1, Videotape 12)
  - VHS tape: Learning Network of Central Ohio: A Conversation with Howard Rheingold (Box 1, Videotape 13)
  - VHS tape: CBS News Sunday Morning "Virtually Everything" Correspondent: Serena Altschul (Box 1, Videotape 14)
  - VHS tape: Rheingold, Howard: ZDTV "Big Thinkers" Interview: 11/3/1999 Approx. 20 mins.: Keynote Speakers, Palo Alto CA (Box 1, Videotape 15)
  - VHS tape: Howard Rheingold, Syndicated Technology Columnist, Exec Editor: WIRED On Line, Excerpts with: Carles Kuralt - CBS, Sam Donaldson - ABC, Sonya Live - CNN, Chicago Tonight - NBC, Sprint Corporation, Original, 1994, 10 mins. (Box 1, Videotape 16)
  - VHS tape (commercial): Synthetic Pleasures, Iara Lee, Caipirinha Productions (Box 1, Videotape 17)
  - VHS tape: An MQN Production for FRONTLINE "High Stakes in Cyberspace" Time: 51:00 (Box 1, Videotape 18)
  - VHS tape: John Nathan Productions NEC Global College TRT 10:31 8/12/1997 (Box 1, Videotape 19)
  - VHS tape: CBS News First Item on Taper "Virtual Reality" Segment with Howard Rheingold, 02/14/1992 (Box 1, Videotape 20)
  - VHS tape: Howard Rheingold, International Telecommunication Carriers Speech, Las Vegas, 12/09/1997 (Box 1, Videotape 21)
  - VHS tape: Howard Rheingold, 1994 Sprint Business Users' Association Conference, 04/28/1994 (Box 1, Videotape 23)
  - VHS tape: Rhiengold, Howard. Technology, communication, and the Internet. Stanford University Television Network, 12/07/1995; mold on tape pack (Box 1, Videotape 24)
  - VHS tape: Rhiengold, Howard. Learn Tech '95. speech given at New Brunswick Community college - Miramachi, 05/05/1995 (Box 1, Videotape 25)
  - VHS tape: Comdex Interactive week. ZDTV, 05/05/1995 (Box 1, Videotape 26)
  - VHS tape: Rhiengold, Howard. Community Space & Cypberspace Conference Keynote Address, 01/1997 (Box 1, Videotape 27)
  - VHS tape: Howard Rheingold Excerpts Demo CBS-ABC-CNN, 1994- (Box 1, Videotape 28)
  - VHS tape: Boulder Community Network 3.00 Raw Dub With Howard Rheingold (Box 1, Videotape 29)
  - VHS tape: The Internet Cafe "Electronic Communities" TIC 105. PCTV, 1997 (Box 1, Videotape 30)
  - VHS tape: Rhiengold, Howard. Television Interview/Conversation about two of his books: Millenium Whole Earth Catalog and Virtual Community, 1994 (Box 1, Videotape 31)
  - VHS tape: Howard Rheingold BBC Horizon (Box 1, Videotape 32)
  - VHS tape: Authors @ MIT: Howard Rheingold, Smart Mobs, 10/22/2002 (Box 1, Videotape 33)
  - VHS tape (commercial): Livin' On the Net with Howard Rheingold Vol.1. E-Mail, Newsgroups, FAQ's, & Virtual Communities (Michael Wiese Production) (Box 1, Videotape 34)
  - U-Matic tape: Martian Promos 1) Fan Club; 2) Advertising appeal (Box 3, Videotape 1)
  - U-Matic tape: Martian Report #1 1) Financial, Computers. Berkeley. Neidhardt/Rheingold (Box 3, Videotape 2)
  - U-Matic tape: Martian Report #5. Neidhardt/Rheingold (Box 3, Videotape 3)
  - U-Matic tape: Martian Report #8. Two Programs. 1) Field Techniques; 2) Archaeology. USC Football (Box 3, Videotape 4)
  - U-Matic tape: Martian Report #9 1) Tourists Bus; 2) Doggie; 3) Civic Center Solar NSG. Neidhardt/Rheingold (Box 3, Videotape 5)
  - 3 DVD-Rs: Martian Reports #1, 5 & 9 (Box 3)
- Series II: Documents and Ephemera
  - How to Paint Your Shoes: 2 vols. and DVD (Half-box 2, Folder 1)
  - Rheingold Books: "War of the Gurus" and "1994" (2 vols.) (Half-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Martian Report flier, other handbills (Half-box 2, Folder 3)
  - Electricminds (Half-box 2, Folder 4)
  - New Technology Coloring Book (Half-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Rheingold thesis: "What Life Can Compare with This?" (Half-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tomorrow column, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - photographs: Bob Taylor 7 Doug Engelbart at DEC Systems Research Center, Palo Alto, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Howard Rheingold, Virtual Landscape (New Dimensions, 2 audiocassettes), 1995 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - typescripts: The California Bug 12/9/1985; The Writer of Tomrrow c.1980, 1980-1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - notebooks and business cards (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Travels in Virtual Reality, 2 drafts (one for Psychology Today, one for Whole Earth Review) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Memoranda of Agreement: Virtual Communities, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Smart Mobs proposal, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Tools for Thought notes, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Articles by or about Rheingold [unfoldered], circa 1976-2003 (Box 4)
- Series III: Digitial Objects